Hemlock Society of Southern Arizona records, 1983-1991 (bulk, 1988-1991)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Hemlock Society of Southern Arizona records, 1983-1991 (bulk, 1988-1991)
MS 301
Hemlock Society of Southern Arizona
This collection is comprised of six series: Organizational Materials, 1983-1990. Correspondence, 1987-1990. Legal Materials. Talks, 1984-1991. Conferences, 1984-1991. Printed Materials, 1981-1991. Correspondence, minutes, bylaws, leaflets, clippings, and books pertaining to their activities. The correspondence pertains to the proposed Death with Dignity Act; some is with the organization Americans Against Human Suffering. Legal materials involve both the Society and general euthanasia issues. The transcripts are of talks delivered in Tucson and Phoenix. Some records pertain to the 1988 Supreme Court case of Cruzan vs. Harmon. Newsletters from the National Hemlock Society and regional societies are included.
1.25 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
The Hemlock Society of Southern Arizona was formed around 1983 and incorporated in 1988 as a nonprofit corporation. It is one of many state and regional Hemlock societies in the United States. The expressed purpose of the Society is to educate the general public regarding right-to-die issues. The Society seeks to promote its goals by such means as newsletters and other printed materials, conferences, and court cases.
Organization
This collection is organized into six series:
I. Organizational Materials
II. Correspondence
III. Legal Materials
IV. Talks
V. Conferences
VI. Printed Materials
Scope and Content Note
The Organizational Materials, 1983-1990, are subdivided into Minutes, Bylaws, and Forms/Leaflets. The Minutes include not only records of topics discussed at meetings, but also treasurer's reports on the Society's financial status. The Bylaws include a general guide for the formation and structure of local Hemlock societies. The Forms and Leaflets consist of questions and answers about the Hemlock Society, membership applications, and a catalog of Hemlock Society videos.
The Correspondence, 1987-1990, consists of letters and miscellaneous items pertaining to the proposed "Death With Dignity" Act, and correspondence from the organization "Americans Against Human Suffering."
The Legal Materials include forms and brochures concerning both the Hemlock Society of Southern Arizona and euthanasia issues in general.
The Talks are transcripts of euthanasia-related speeches sponsored by the Society and delivered in Tucson and Phoenix from 1984-1991.
The Conferences, 1984-1991, consist of a collection of articles, correspondence, and reports dealing primarily with meetings sponsored by the Society, along with a set of brochures, papers, and correspondence pertaining to various other euthanasia-related conferences.
The Printed Materials, 1981-1991, are subdivided into Definitions, Clippings, Legal Cases, Newsletters, and Books. The Definitions are of key terms encountered in discussions of the right-to-die issue. The Clippings consist of newspaper and magazine articles about hemlock societies and euthanasia. The Legal Cases are court records, and summaries of court records, from cases involving the question of euthanasia. Most of these records pertain to the 1988 Supreme Court case of Cruzan vs. Harmon. The Newsletters include newsletters from not only the Hemlock Society of Southern Arizona, but also from the National Hemlock Society and several other state and regional hemlock societies. Finally, there are four books, one booklet, and six issues of the journal The Euthanasia Review.
Access Terms
Hemlock Society of Southern Arizona
Americans Against Human Suffering
Hemlock (Society)
Euthanasia
Right to Die
Correspondence
Bylaws
Minutes
Container List
- Organizational Materials, 1983-1990
  - Minutes of meetings, treasurer's reports, bylaws, guide to formation of Hemlock societies, question-and-answer leaflets, video catalog, and membership applications. 1983-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
- Correspondence, 1987-1990
  - Letters and miscellaneous materials regarding the proposed "Death With Dignity" Act, and correspondence from the "Americans Against Human Suffering" organization. 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
- Legal materials, No Date
  - Legal forms and brochures pertaining both to the Hemlock Society of Southern Arizona and to euthanasia issues in general. No Date (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Talks, 1984-1990
  - Texts of talks given in Tucson and Phoenix concerning the right-to-die issue. 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Conferences, 1984-1990
  - Brochures, reports, correspondence, and articles regarding various euthanasia-related conferences. 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
- Printed materials, 1981-1991
  - Clippings, court records, newsletters, books, and journals. 1981-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12-19)